<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<protocol name="hyprland_global_shortcuts_v1">
  <copyright>
    Copyright © 2022 Vaxry
    All rights reserved.

    Redistribution and use in source and binary forms, with or without
    modification, are permitted provided that the following conditions are met:

    1. Redistributions of source code must retain the above copyright notice, this
       list of conditions and the following disclaimer.

    2. Redistributions in binary form must reproduce the above copyright notice,
       this list of conditions and the following disclaimer in the documentation
       and/or other materials provided with the distribution.

    3. Neither the name of the copyright holder nor the names of its
       contributors may be used to endorse or promote products derived from
       this software without specific prior written permission.

    THIS SOFTWARE IS PROVIDED BY THE COPYRIGHT HOLDERS AND CONTRIBUTORS "AS IS"
    AND ANY EXPRESS OR IMPLIED WARRANTIES, INCLUDING, BUT NOT LIMITED TO, THE
    IMPLIED WARRANTIES OF MERCHANTABILITY AND FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE ARE
    DISCLAIMED. IN NO EVENT SHALL THE COPYRIGHT HOLDER OR CONTRIBUTORS BE LIABLE
    FOR ANY DIRECT, INDIRECT, INCIDENTAL, SPECIAL, EXEMPLARY, OR CONSEQUENTIAL
    DAMAGES (INCLUDING, BUT NOT LIMITED TO, PROCUREMENT OF SUBSTITUTE GOODS OR
    SERVICES; LOSS OF USE, DATA, OR PROFITS; OR BUSINESS INTERRUPTION) HOWEVER
    CAUSED AND ON ANY THEORY OF LIABILITY, WHETHER IN CONTRACT, STRICT LIABILITY,
    OR TORT (INCLUDING NEGLIGENCE OR OTHERWISE) ARISING IN ANY WAY OUT OF THE USE
    OF THIS SOFTWARE, EVEN IF ADVISED OF THE POSSIBILITY OF SUCH DAMAGE.
  </copyright>

  <description summary="registering global shortcuts">
    This protocol allows a client to register triggerable actions,
    meant to be global shortcuts.
  </description>

  <interface name="hyprland_global_shortcuts_manager_v1" version="1">
    <description summary="manager to register global shortcuts">
      This object is a manager which offers requests to create global shortcuts.
    </description>

    <request name="register_shortcut">
      <description summary="register a shortcut">
        Register a new global shortcut.

        A global shortcut is anonymous, meaning the app does not know what key(s) trigger it.

        The shortcut's keybinding shall be dealt with by the compositor.

        In the case of a duplicate app_id + id combination, the already_taken protocol error is raised.
      </description>
      <arg name="shortcut" type="new_id" interface="hyprland_global_shortcut_v1"/>
      <arg name="id" type="string" summary="a unique id for the shortcut"/>
      <arg name="app_id" type="string" summary="the app_id of the application requesting the shortcut"/>
      <arg name="description" type="string" summary="user-readable text describing what the shortcut does."/>
      <arg name="trigger_description" type="string" summary="user-readable text describing how to trigger the shortcut for the client to render."/>
    </request>

    <request name="destroy" type="destructor">
      <description summary="destroy the manager">
        All objects created by the manager will still remain valid, until their
        appropriate destroy request has been called.
      </description>
    </request>

    <enum name="error">
      <entry name="already_taken" value="0"
        summary="the app_id + id combination has already been registered."/>
    </enum>
  </interface>

  <interface name="hyprland_global_shortcut_v1" version="1">
    <description summary="a shortcut">
      This object represents a single shortcut.
    </description>

    <event name="pressed">
      <description summary="keystroke pressed">
        The keystroke was pressed.

        tv_ values hold the timestamp of the occurrence.
      </description>
      <arg name="tv_sec_hi" type="uint"
           summary="high 32 bits of the seconds part of the timestamp"/>
      <arg name="tv_sec_lo" type="uint"
           summary="low 32 bits of the seconds part of the timestamp"/>
      <arg name="tv_nsec" type="uint"
           summary="nanoseconds part of the timestamp"/>
    </event>

    <event name="released">
      <description summary="keystroke released">
        The keystroke was released.

        tv_ values hold the timestamp of the occurrence.
      </description>
      <arg name="tv_sec_hi" type="uint"
           summary="high 32 bits of the seconds part of the timestamp"/>
      <arg name="tv_sec_lo" type="uint"
           summary="low 32 bits of the seconds part of the timestamp"/>
      <arg name="tv_nsec" type="uint"
           summary="nanoseconds part of the timestamp"/>
    </event>

    <request name="destroy" type="destructor">
      <description summary="delete this object, used or not">
        Destroys the shortcut. Can be sent at any time by the client.
      </description>
    </request>
  </interface>
</protocol>
